Okay, בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף Daf is בבא בתרא ו׳,
Bava Batra Vav, בבא בתרא Bava Batra six, and we are right
on schedule and we pick up on the last line or the
second to last line on עמוד ב׳, Amud Bet, and we just
finished a discussion about whether if somebody sets a time for a
payment back of a loan, pay me back, you know, by day
thirty, specifically designates the due date, and then is a person believed
to say they paid up before the time arrived or not, do
we say חזקה דאין אדם פורע בתוך זמנו? Chazakah de'ein adam porei
betoch zemano? And that was the גמרא's Gemara conclusion, that we said
חזקה לא עביד איניש דפרע בגו זימנא, Hazaka lo avid inish deparei
bego zimnei, and therefore even though we would normally say המוציא מחברו
עליו הראיה, Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, if somebody claims that they've already
paid up, they are not believed if they paid up during the
actual time. Now the גמרא Gemara is going to build on that.
So let's take a look. איבעיא להו, Ibayah lehu, they raised the
question: תבעו אחר זמן ואמר לו פרעתיך בתוך זמני מהו? Tava'o achar
zman ve'amar lo peraticha betoch zemani mahu? Let's say the creditor said
to the debtor, it was after the thirty days, and he said,
"Give me my money." And now, if the debtor had said, "I
paid you now," like, "I paid you yesterday," let's say after the
thirty days were up, he would be believed. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה,
Hamotzi mechavero alav hara'aya, you might have to make a שבועת היסת,
Shevuat hesset, but basically you're believed. But he didn't say, "I paid
you yesterday" and the time was already up. He said, "I paid
you last week when it was still during the period of the
loan, when the loan was not yet due." All right, so would
we apply a מיגו? Migo? If he had said he had paid
him, we would say he had paid him after the loan was
due, he would be believed, so can that give him a מיגו
Migo to believe him when he said he paid him even before
the loan was due?
Okay, מהו, Mahu, what's the הלכה? Halacha? מי אמרינן במקום חזקה אמרינן
מה לי לשקר? Mi amrinan bimkom chazaka amrinan ma li leshaker? Do
we say that מה לי לשקר, Ma li leshaker, which is another
word for מיגו, Migo, "Why would he bother lying?" And here there's
like really no incentive to lie, you know, say that you paid,
who cares if you say you paid him last week or you
say you paid him yesterday? So, and he actually has absolutely no
reason to lie, so and since he would have been believed to
say he paid you yesterday, let's believe him that he said he
paid you last week. That's a
מיגו. Migo. או דילמא במקום חזקה לא אמרינן מה לי לשקר? O
dilma bimkom chazaka lo amrinan ma li leshaker? When it's running up
against a חזקה, Chazakah, the חזקה Chazakah is like a strong presumption
of behavior here. חזקה Chazakah can mean different things, but חזקה לא
עביד איניש דפרע בגו זימנא, Hazaka lo avid inish deparei bego zimnei,
we are so certain that people do not pay up during the
time, that even though there's like a persuasive argument, "Come on, you
should believe him, if he wanted to lie, he would have said
he paid yesterday," nevertheless that claim is so unbelievable, non-believable, that we
do not believe him. And interestingly, not only does he have a
מיגו, Migo, he's the one that's מוחזק Muchzak in the money, and
nevertheless this חזקה Chazakah might be so strong that that claim is
not believed even with a מיגו. Migo. תא שמע, Ta shema, so
let's come in here. בבחזקת שנתן עד שיביא ראיה שלא נתן. Bechezkat
shenatan ad sheyavi re'aya shelo natan. Okay, so now we're going to
try to bring a proof from our משנה, Mishnah, which was the
whole reason we got into this discussion. בבחזקת שנתן עד שיביא ראיה
שלא נתן. Bechezkat shenatan ad sheyavi re'aya shelo natan. Okay, so the
משנה Mishnah says that if the person, you know, for the first
ארבע אמות, Arba amot, when a wall fell down and has to
be rebuilt, and the obligation is to build it up to ארבע
אמות Arba amot and both sides are obligated, if the person, you
know, one person was building and the other person said, "Yeah, I
paid my half," he's believed. Okay, so let's take a look at
exactly what the context is. That's a case where clearly he had
an obligation to pay and he's believed to say that he paid.
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the case? אילימא שתבעו אחר זמן ואמר
לו פרעתיך בזמני פשיטא. Ilima shetava'o achar zman ve'amar lo peraticha bizmani
peshita. If the guy who was building the wall said after he
built the wall, "Give me my money," and he said, "Yes, I
paid you the money when the time came," meaning after the wall
was built, so it's obvious he'd be believed. That's a classic case
of כופר הכל, Kofer hakol, somebody says you owe me the money
and he says that I've already paid you, and you know, and
he's believed, that's a כופר הכל Kofer hakol and he's believed with
maybe a שבועת היסת. Shevuat hesset. Okay, so then it would be
obvious if he said, "I paid you once the time had come,
once you finished building the wall." אלא לאו, Ela lav, it must
be, so if the משנה Mishnah is teaching you a חידוש, Chidush,
it must be something a little bit more out of the ordinary.
דאמר לו פרעתיך בתוך זמני, De'amar lo peraticha betoch zemani, that no,
that he came after the wall was finished being built, and the
other guy said, "I paid you, you know, even when you were
in the middle of building the wall." And that's maybe the חידוש
Chidush of the משנה, Mishnah, that even then he's believed. מיגו, Migo,
he could have said "I paid you yesterday after the wall was
done." So עלמא אפילו במקום חזקה אמרינן מה לי לשקר, Alma afilu
bimkom chazaka amrinan ma li leshaker, so clearly you see you would
say a מיגו Migo even against this חזקה Chazakah that people don't
pay within the time. So because we want to make the משנה
Mishnah have to say something interesting, we're going to assume that it
speaks directly to our case. So the גמרא Gemara says, "No, like
we saw yesterday, this is all sort of a little echo of
yesterday, שאני הכא דכל שפא ושפא זימנא הוא. Shani hacha dekol shafa
veshafa zman hu. Here it's different. Every brick is the time." Okay,
so therefore, you know,
every expenditure that the guy makes
building. reimburse him. So it's not just you're obligated after the whole
wall is being built, you're obligated every step along the way to
reimburse the guy for his expenses and his effort. So in that
case, even if the משנה mishna was talking about what you said
it was talking about, that he says he claims he paid him,
you know, during the time before it got finished, he would be
believed because of there's no תוך זמן toch zman there. Everything is
in a way after the זמן. zman. There's always an obligation that
is that, you know, that my to pay because the work is
all the previous work had just been done. Okay, what's not so
clear is, you know, that if he said let's say I paid
you on day one for the entire expenses, right? So just because
after day one he was obligated for one day's of labor and
the expenditure of day one, that doesn't sort of, you know, explain
why he would be believed to say he paid him for all
the future expenses. So it's not exactly clear, wasn't exactly clear yesterday
either why just because every day the debt is increasing, that means
that he's believed to say that he paid the full amount earlier.
But nevertheless, the גמרא gemara seems to be saying, look, if this
is an ongoing incurring debt, it's not like I say you don't
have to owe me anything but by day thirty that's when you're
obligated. Here, since it's an ongoing incurred debt, therefore it's always a
sense of obligation and it seems like he would be believed to
say that he paid the full amount even earlier on. Okay, תא
שמע, ta shma, come and hear. מארבע אמות ולמעלה אין מחייבין אותו.
mearba amot ulemala ein mechayvin oto. So if it's four אמות amot
higher than four אמות, amot, if the one of the guys decides
to build it higher than four אמות, amot, since there's no obligation
because there's no היזק ראיה hezek re'iyah after that, there is no
then the other person has no obligation to chip in after four
אמות. amot. אין מחייבין אותו. ein mechayvin oto. סמך לו כותל אחר,
samach lo kotel acher, but however if the guy who wasn't building
higher decided to then put a wall, build a wall in his
property, you know, at the same height so that he could then
make use of this higher part of the wall, then it's showing
that he wants that higher wall and he's considered to be a
partner in it and he has to pay for that higher part
as well. Okay, so מארבע אמות ולמעלה אין מחייבין אותו, mearba amot
ulemala ein mechayvin oto, סמך לו כותל אחר, samach lo kotel acher,
etc., and it says, you know, he is בחזקה שלא נתן bechezaka
shelo natan and we assume that since it is as the גמרא
gemara will say, it's not taken for granted that he's obligated to
pay, so we are presuming he's not he hasn't paid until he
can bring proof that he has paid. So in this case, even
if he says he paid, he's not believed unless he's able to
bring proof. Okay, so how is this different than the previous case?
Let's take a look. היכי דמי, heichi dami, what's the case? אילימא
דתבעו לאחר זמנו ואמר לו פרעתיך בזמני, ilima detav'o le'achar zmano ve'amar
lo paraticha bizmani, if he made the demand after the wall was
finished being built and the guy said, you know, I paid you
after the whole wall was finished, so
אמאי לא, amai lo, why shouldn't he be believed? It's a classic
case of כופר הכל kofer hakol and let him be believed to
say that he paid up. אלא לאו דאמר פרעתיך בתוך זמני. ela
lav de'amar paraticha betoch zmani. So let's say, similar to what we
were claiming before about the previous case, that he said I paid
you while the extra higher height over four אמות amot was being
built and that's why he's not believed. Okay, פרעתיך בתוך זמני, paraticha
betoch zmani, אלמא במקום חזקה לא אמרינן מה לי לשקר. alma bemakom
chazaka lo amrinan mah li lishaker. That must be why he's not
be believed because it goes against the חזקה chazaka that people don't
pay up during the time before the debt is due. Now that's
very strange because, you know, clearly there's a difference between the first
case of the משנה mishna about the first four אמות amot and
the higher four אמות. amot. If the reason he wasn't be believed
in the second half of the משנה mishna was because he's not
believed to say, you know, while the before the debt is due,
what does that have to do with the first four or the
second four אמות? amot? Also, as we have already established, in the
building of the wall, you know, it's an ongoing debt. So obviously
that's a very bad אוקימתא okimta of the גמרא, gemara, but whatever,
the גמרא gemara is trying to say maybe that's what it's saying
and that's why he's not believed because he's making the claim that
he paid during the period before it was due and that מיגו
migo doesn't work against the חזקה. chazaka. So the
גמרא gemara says no, שאני הכא דאמר מר, shani hacha de'amar mar,
no, here it's
different because we say מי יימר דמחייבי לי רבנן? mi yeimar demichayvu
li rabanan? No, the guy, you know, he knows higher than four
אמות amot he's not obligated and it's not generally known that if
you build a parallel wall then you do become obligated. So since
he has no he assumes that he's not obligated and the neighbor
might be saying, I'm telling you, now that you built a wall
you have to pay half, like he's skeptical and he is, it's
presumed that he's not going to pay until the בית דין beit
din obligates him. So even after the debt is incurred, here he
is not believed to say, you know, that I paid because this
would be a חזקה chazaka basically that he is going to assume
he's not obligated until the בית דין beit din assumes that he
is. And that's obvious the difference between the first four אמות amot
and the higher height of the wall. Okay, אמר ליה, amar lei,
so we tried to prove it from the משנה, mishna, but obviously
it was a bad attempt. something into the Mishnah that wasn't there
and we do not know the answer to whether a מיגו migo
works against this חזקה chazakah that people do not pay within their
time.
Okay. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי amar lei Rav
Acha brei deRava leRav Ashi תא שמע. ta shma.
So we're going to try to prove it from somewhere else. Come
and hear. מנה לי בידך, maneh li beyadecha, אמר לו הן. amar
lo hein. So Reuven says to Shimon, you owe me a hundred
dollars, or you borrowed a hundred dollars. And Shimon says, yes, I
admit that I borrowed a hundred dollars. Okay. למחר אמר לו תנהו
לי lemachar amar lo tnehu li and then the next day Reuven
comes to Shimon and says, give me that hundred dollars that you
admitted to me yesterday. אם אמר נתתיו לך פטור. im amar netativ
lach patur. If Shimon says, I paid you up, he's exempt, you
know. Yesterday I admitted I owed you the money and between yesterday
and today I paid you. All right? And that's a classic case
again of a כופר הכל. kofer hakol.
אין לך בידי חייב. ein lacha beyadi chayav. But if Shimon says,
you know, there was never a debt, then he's obligated. Obviously he's
obligated because
he's
contradicting his own admission yesterday when he said there was a debt.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara tries to do with this.
It seems pretty straightforward. מאי לאו נתתיו לך דאמר ליה פרעתיך בזמני,
mai lav netativ lach de'amar lei para'eticha bizmani, אין לך בידי דאמר
ליה פרעתיך בתוך זמני? ein lacha beyadi de'amar lei para'eticha betoch zamni?
Because the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to assume that the second part
where he says, you know, you don't have any debt, there is
no debt, is not a case where he just denied that he
ever borrowed the money. That would be obvious that, you know, he's
just contradicting what he said yesterday. So to make this interesting we're
going to say the following: that when he said I paid you
means I paid you after, you know, the debt was due and
then he's believed. When he says אין לך בידי ein lacha beyadi
means that means he's not saying I never borrowed the money. He's
saying, you know, that debt never made it to completion. You never
even, you know, when the debt came due it was already paid
off. That's what we're going to claim that phrase means. And then
the חידוש chiddush of the ברייתא Braisa here would be that you
do not believe him. Even though he has a מיגו migo that
he could have said I paid it when it became due, if
he's saying it never reached maturity because I prepaid it, he's not
believed. So maybe that's exactly, that this ברייתא Braisa is proving that
you, the מיגו migo does not work.
אלא במקום חזקה לא אמרינן מה לי לשקר. ela bimkom chazakah lo
amrinan mah li leshaker. So you see, you do not say why
would he bother lying, you don't have a מיגו, migo, that it
does not work against this חזקה chazakah that people do not pay
up within their time. So the גמרא Gemara says לא. lo. No.
מאי אין לך בידי לא היו דברים מעולם. mai ein lacha beyadi
lo hayu devarim me'olam. So no, it's not saying that. It's just
saying that he completely denies it and, you know, of course if
he completely denies it it's not much of a חידוש chiddush because
yesterday he admitted it now he denies it obviously he's not believed.
But okay, but that's what it's saying. דאמר מר de'amar mar because
we teach, כל האומר לא לויתי כאומר לא פרעתי דמי, kol ha'omer
lo livisi ke'omer lo parati dami, anybody who denies that they have
borrowed is essentially saying that they did not pay up. Now the
question is, did you really need this here? Because, you know, here
he just is contradicting what he said before. What's the point of
saying oh by saying you didn't borrow you're implicitly saying you did
not pay? So תוספות Tosafos asks this question and תוספות Tosafos says
it just means that he's not believed to interpret what he said
and say when I said I didn't borrow the money from you
I meant that I'd already paid it up. And the גמרא Gemara
is saying you're not believed to interpret it that way. When you
say you didn't borrow it means you didn't borrow and, you know,
and your claim is very clear and therefore that is not believed
because yesterday you admitted that you did borrow. Okay, so we do
not come to a conclusion about this issue about, about whether the
מיגו migo can work against a חזקה chazakah that people do not
pay up during the time that the loan is still, is not
yet due. All right, now we move on. אמר רב הונא amar
Rav Huna סמך לפלגא סמך לכולא. samach lepalga samach lekula. So now
we're going to get finally back to the משנה Mishnah and Rav
Huna is saying like this. Let's say you go ahead and you
build this wall, right, Reuven built the wall שמונה אמות. shmonah amos.
So the first ארבע אמות arba amos Shimon was חייב. chayav. Let's
say actually say ten אמות. amos. The first ארבע אמות arba amos
Shimon was חייב. chayav. The next six from four to ten Shimon
is not חייב. chayav. But if Shimon then builds a parallel wall,
it makes it clear that he's planning to use this extra height
that Reuven built, then Shimon is now obligated to pay half for
the higher six אמות amos as well. All right, so Rav Huna
says סמך לפלגא סמך לכולא. samach lepalga samach lekula. Even if Shimon
did not build the entire height of Reuven's wall, he only built
it up eight אמות, amos, not ten, or he only built it,
he didn't build the entire length. You know, let's say the wall
runs a hundred feet and he only built a parallel wall fifty
feet, he says nevertheless we are going to consider it that that's
an indication that you're planning on using the entire extent, height of
the, you know, ten feet and the entire length of it and
you have to pay for everything that was done. This is a
little bit questionable. How do you know just because he wants to
use some of the wall he wants to use the whole part
of it? But that's what Rav Huna says. רב נחמן אמר למאי
דסמך סמך למאי דלא סמך לא סמך Rav Nachman amar lemai desamach
samach lemai delo samach lo samach and Rav Nachman says the more
reasonable position, no. The part that he made parallel he made parallel
in height and in length, and if he only went up eight
אמות, amos, you make him pay up to eight אמות, amos, you
don't make him pay for from the eight to 10, and if
he only made it go 50 feet then you only make him
pay for the 50 feet extension and not the extra and not
the whole 100 feet. Okay. מודה רב הונא בקרנא דאלופתא. Modeh Rav
Huna bekarna de-alufta. Now רב הונא Rav Huna agrees in a corner
and the אלופתא alufta which תוספות Tosafot explains, רש"י Rashi has one
explanation but we'll go with תוספות's Tosafot explanation. תוספות Tosafot explains what
it means is similar to like the גמרא Gemara had something like
this before: if he basically makes a curl at the end. So
if he at the height of the wall he made it eight
feet and then he curled the top, it's clear he's not going
to continue building higher to the 10 feet. If he did 50
feet and he curled it at the edge, it's clear he's not
going to build the whole 100 feet. So in that
case רב הונא Rav Huna would agree
that it's clear he's only going to use that part of it
and you don't make him pay half for the whole thing. ומודה
רב נחמן באפריזא ובכבושא
דכשורי. U-modeh Rav Nachman be-afriza u-be-kivasa de-kshurei. And similarly here the,
excuse
me,
sorry hold on a second.
So רב נחמן Rav Nachman agrees that you would have to pay
all if what you did was you made it clear at least
this is dealing the way רש"י Rashi explains with the case of
height, if you made it clear that you are going to continue
to build from eight to 10 feet or let's take another example
from eight to 16 feet. What's the scenario? The scenario is that
you are going to build two stories, okay, you're going to use
his wall or the wall between the two of you and the
new wall you built and you're going to make a house and
there're going to be two stories and after the first eight feet
you stopped at eight he built it all the way up to
16 but what you did was you put
a beam on the top of the wall that was going to
be used to laying crossbeams across so that you could make a
roof and on that roof you could continue to build up and
build a second story. So you've laid that. That's the case of
אפריזא afriza and כבושא דכשורי kivasa de-kshurei is a place where you
would insert the crossbeams from your wall to the other wall. And
somehow it's in a way as רש"י Rashi explains that it's not
just clear that you're going to be using this as the roof
but it's going to be the foundation for a second story so
that makes it clear that you're going to use the entire height.
Okay,
let's keep on going. אמר רב הונא בי כווי לא הוי חזקה.
Amar Rav Huna bei kivei lo havei chazaka. Now we're going to
deal with this חזקה chazaka here is not the
חזקה chazaka of the third פרק. perek. The חזקה chazaka of the
third פרק perek is that you are on somebody's property for three
years and you claim
that you bought it and when you're asked to show the שטר
shtar the documentation you say it's like your tax records you can
get rid of them after a certain period of time since nobody
complained in three
years I did not hold on to them and I don't have
them and you're believed. That's a חזקה chazaka of three years which
comes with a claim that you purchased the land. Okay. This is
different. This is a case where your silence constitutes an acceptance of
the situation and it's a type of an evidence that you were
מוחל. mochel. So
this is different. This is a case where the חזקה chazaka is
a proof of either again that somebody
was agreed to allow a certain situation to continue a type of
a מחילה mechila of rights or in the first case we're going
to apply it to as a type of an evidence
that the debt was paid. Okay, so it's a very broad use
of the word חזקה. chazaka. So בי כווי bei kivei which is
again these holes for these crossbeams are not a חזקה. chazaka. What
does that mean they're not a חזקה? chazaka?
Meaning שמעון Shimon built the wall between the two of them and
he built it up to 10 feet and then he made holes
in the wall let's say at the 10 feet height or at
the 8 feet height that could be used by ראובן Reuven if
ראובן Reuven were to build a parallel wall could be used by
ראובן Reuven to put in the crossbeams. So it's clear that שמעון
Shimon is anticipating that ראובן Reuven is going to put in the
crossbeams and ראובן Reuven says I've already paid you for that extra
height the evidence is that you made those holes. If I hadn't
paid you then you would not have accommodated me by making those
holes so clearly we were already partners in that extra height or
you would not have built it in with those holes. That seems
like a reasonable claim. But let's take a look. So it says
why? ואף על גב דעביד ליה הימלי לא. Ve-af al gav de-avid
lei himlei lo. Even if he made the holes even if he
put the הימלי himlei which רש"י Rashi says are like wood paddings
within the holes to accept the beams so even though all of
that was done that would have accommodated
ראובן's Reuven wall nevertheless ראובן Reuven cannot use it as a proof
that he partially paid. Why? דאמר ליה אמינא דלכי פייסת לי לא
לישתעי. De-amar lei amina de-lechi payastei li lo lishat-ei. אשיתאי ashitai
cause שמעון Shimon can say, "No, I knew you were going to
have to pay me, I anticipated that you were going to build
it," or maybe, I don't know, maybe ראובן's Reuven's already built his
parallel wall, still the question is did ראובן Reuven pay שמעון? Shimon?
And שמעון Shimon is saying, "I knew that that was going to
be the situation, that you were going to build the wall, that
you were going to want to put the crossbeams, and I figured
better to be prepared and better to make it with the holes
from the outset rather than to wait for you to build your
parallel wall and pay me for my half, and then we would
have to make new holes, and that would actually damage the wall.
So yes, I did it anticipating it, but that does not mean
that you actually have paid me." All right. אמר רב נחמן. Amar
Rav Nachman. אחזיק להורדי לא אחזיק לכשורי, לכשורי אחזיק להורדי. Ahzik l'hurdi
lo ahzik l'kshuri, l'kshuri ahzik l'hurdi. And this is a חזקה, chazaka,
again, more of like, you know, rights. If I am sort of
using—I've demonstrated I have some rights, you know, or I've done a
certain activity and you haven't protested, is it proof that I have
those rights? So he says that if somebody, basically, forget the case
here of the, you know, about do you have to build, pay
for the height for the higher, you know, wall or whatever. Let's
just say there's a wall in somebody in—totally in ראובן's Reuven's field.
On the border, but totally on ראובן's Reuven's side. It's ראובן's Reuven's
wall. And שמעון Shimon builds his own wall in his field and
he puts a crossbeam on it and it rests on top of
ראובן's Reuven's wall. And ראובן Reuven doesn't say anything. So that silence
is sort of like an acquiescence that שמעון Shimon has the right
to do it. Now, there's an interesting discussion in the ראשונים, Rishonim,
is it just that the silence is the acquiescence itself, or does
שמעון Shimon have to make a claim, and does שמעון Shimon have
to say, "You explicitly gave me the rights, you know, transferred me,
sold me, gifted me, whatever it was, agreed to give me the
rights to use your wall to put my crossbeams"? So that's a
really important question. Is it that the silence needs to be backed
by an explicit claim that it was explicitly done and those rights
were granted, or is it enough just the silence itself shows that
ראובן Reuven is forfeiting, you know, his right to protest? Really, really
important question in, you know, tenant and שכנים shchenim and all those
types of questions. Anyway, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman says that if
you basically—if he had אחזיק להורדי לא אחזיק לכשורי. ahzik l'hurdi lo
ahzik l'kshuri. If he had, you know, established a חזקה, chazaka, meaning
he'd started using his neighbor's wall for—for putting—for putting—like thin
two-by-fours or whatever resting on the wall, that is not considered that
he has established rights to allow him to put on heavy beams,
you know? The guy could say, "Yeah, I was quiet when it
was thin planks; I'm not allowing you to put on heavy beams."
אמר רב נחמן. Amar Rav Nachman.
אחזיק
להורדי לא אחזיק לכשורי, לכשורי אחזיק להורדי. Ahzik l'hurdi lo ahzik l'kshuri,
l'kshuri ahzik l'hurdi. But if שמעון Shimon started using the guy's wall
for heavy beams, then implicitly, and ראובן Reuven didn't say anything, then
implicitly he also has the rights to use them
for thin planks. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amrei, others say, ורב יוסף אמר,
v'Rav Yosef amar, but רב יוסף Rav Yosef says, "No, אחזיק להורדי
אחזיק לכשורי. ahzik l'hurdi ahzik l'kshuri. No, even if for the thin
planks, he is also implicitly rights to use it for the heavy
beams, it's not going to make a really substantial difference in terms
of the wall, so we can assume that one implies the other."
איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amrei, others say, אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman,
אחזיק להורדי אחזיק לכשורי, לכשורי אחזיק להורדי, ahzik l'hurdi ahzik l'kshuri, l'kshuri
ahzik l'hurdi, that רב נחמן Rav Nachman himself said that it works
both ways. אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, similarly, said רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, אחזיק לנטפי אחזיק לשפכי. ahzik l'nitfi ahzik l'shifchi. If somebody
has a roof right next to the neighbor's field and the rain
runs off the roof and hits, you know, hits the neighbor's yard,
so, and the neighbor's not complaining and is allowing it to happen
and is not saying the water damage and you've got to build
a pipe or whatever it is, so if he has a חזקה
chazaka to do it for—for normal dripping, you know, he doesn't really
have a—what do you call it? A—what's that called? A—I'm
losing the word here. The thing that brings the water down. Drainage
pipe. If he doesn't have a drainage pipe, then it all just
runs right off of the roof and hits his neighbor's field, that's
נטפי, nitfi, that's like drops. Okay? So אחזיק לנטפי אחזיק לשפכי. ahzik
l'nitfi ahzik l'shifchi. Then if the neighbor doesn't protest, and that is
implicitly now that he—again, might have to come with a claim that
the neighbor gave him rights, it's a little very unclear, but anyway,
if that establishes, you know, שמעון's Shimon's rights to allow it to
run off into ראובן's Reuven's field, then it also would be if
he would make a drainage pipe, because presumably if it's a drainage
pipe, that's less, you know, all over the place,
it's
in a concentrated place. Of course you could say the opposite: if
it's a heavy amount in a concentrated place, it's worse for ראובן.
Reuven. Anyway, but that's the claim. אחזיק לשפכי לא אחזיק לנטפי. Ahzik
l'shifchi lo ahzik l'nitfi. But even if שמעון Shimon has established a
right to have a drainage pipe with the water running into ראובן's
Reuven's field, that does not give him the right to have the
water run off of his roof and run in all places in
ראובן's Reuven's field. ורב יוסף אמר, v'Rav Yosef amar, ורב יוסף v'Rav
Yosef says, "No, אפילו אחזיק לשפכי אחזיק לנטפי, afilu ahzik l'shifchi ahzik
l'nitfi, that it goes both ways." איכא דאמרי Ika d'amrei others say.
אמר רב נחמן אחזוקי לשופכי אחזוקי לנטפי לנטפי אחזוקי לשופכי. Amar Rav
Nachman achzoki l'shufchi achzoki l'nitfei l'nitfei achzoki l'shufchi. רב נחמן Rav Nachman
himself said it goes both ways, but אבל לצריפא דאורבני לא, aval
l'tzrifa d'urbani lo, but if it is a case of like a
real, you know, like a pointed roof and it comes down in
you know, like a funnel almost or an inverted funnel, but that
the rain, you know, comes down in heavy amounts from the roof
because of the angled roof, then that is not, you cannot jump
from a normal dripping to a scenario like that.
Okay. רב יוסף אמר אפילו צריפא דאורבני, Rav Yosef amar afilu tzrifa
d'urbani, so even in that case, if the guy's okay with the
rain dripping in his in his yard, it would be okay even
if it was a angled roof. עבד רב יוסף, Avad Rav Yosef,
and here we do not have another version that רב נחמן Rav
Nachman said the same thing.
And עבד רב יוסף עובדא בצריפא דאורבני, avad Rav Yosef uvda b'tzrifa
d'urbani, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef actually ruled that way and somebody
had established a right to have the water dripping from his roof
into his neighbor's yard, and רב יוסף Rav Yosef then allowed it
even in a case when it was an angled roof and more
water was was going into the yard. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha, says רב נחמן,
Rav Nachman, says רבה בר אבוה, Rabba bar Avuha, המשכיר בית לחברו
בבירה גדולה. hamaskir bayis l'chavero b'bira gedola. Okay, now we're top of
ו עמוד ב, vov amud bais, somebody who rents a house, we
would call it a room, but you know some their rooms sometimes
was a house, would rent a a room a house a room
to his friend in a big castle, so you rent somebody a
room in a big building, you know, like a people have a
house, you know college kids will often do this, and you know
they rent each room as a separate person. Okay. משתמש בזיזי ובכותלי
עד ארבע אמות. Mishtamesh b'zizay u'b'kotlei ad arba amos. You can use
the the protrusions and the walls that come, you know that extend
beyond the exact walls of the room
itself. Imagine, you know, the room is in one corner and there's,
you know, a wall to each side of the room on the
outside of it and protrusions from the wall, and they're outside of
the exact walls of the room, they're extended, they're part of the
walls of the whole house. So he has rights to use it
up to four amot is considered that that is also part of
what he has rented, part of what he has rights to. ובעובי
הכותל במקום שנהגו, U'v'ovi hakosel bimkom shenahagu,
and in the, you know, thickness of the wall, so Rashi says
that means like the top of the wall, not just to stick
things in the hole at the bottom of the wall, but at
the top of the wall, when that's the practice, that's also included.
Okay.
Okay, so that's about the wall, the extension of the wall and
the thickness of the wall. אבל בתרביץ אפדני לא, Aval b'tarbitz apadni
lo, but not in the garden that is like in front of
the building, even if it's I guess against his wall, that's considered
to be not for use for the tenants. רב נחמן דידיה אמר
אפילו בתרביץ אפדני, Rav Nachman didei amar afilu b'tarbitz apadni, but רב
נחמן Rav Nachman himself said no, even that sort of garden in
front of the building or in front of his room, he has
rights to. אבל רחבה שאחורי הבתים לא, Aval rechova she-achorei ha-batim lo,
but like the back alley, no, that's not considered to be included.
ורבא אמר אפילו רחבה שאחורי הבתים. V'Rava amar afilu rechova she-achorei ha-batim.
No, even the back alley. Fine. אמר רבינא, Amar Ravina, האי כישורא
דמטללתא, hai kishura d'matlulassa, a beam of a sukkah, and
now sukkah here does not necessarily mean a mitzvah, a sukkah of
mitzvah, we'll get to that in a minute, but it just means
a a hut, but essentially something that looks like a sukkah. So
you have a beam on the top. עד תלתין יומין לא הוי
חזקה. Ad taltin yomin lo hovei chazaka. So you have your your,
you know, little hut in your yard and you're resting the crossbeam,
like the roof beams, on top of the neighbor's wall, just like
the case before, and the neighbor isn't saying anything. So until what
at what stage is it established that he has been silent and
therefore we can bring that as evidence that you now have, you
know, he's giving you he's forfeiting any right to complain and you
have ongoing rights to use the walls. It's a fascinating idea that
the Gemara just takes it for granted that his silence constitutes, you
know, giving you, you know, indefinite rights on this. Um, again, maybe
it might have to be backed up with a claim that you're
making that he gave it to you. Anyway, so he says, if
you're doing it up to 30 days, that's not a chazaka because
you know he'll let you do it for a brief period of
time, that does not prove that you have ongoing rights to use
it. Okay, so עד תלתין יומין לא הוי חזקה בתר תלתין יומין
הוי חזקה, ad taltin yomin lo hovei chazaka basar taltin yomin hovei
chazaka, more than 30 days and he doesn't say anything, that establishes
that you have rights. ואי סוכה דמצוה היא, V'ei sukkah d'mitzvah hee,
and if it is the sukkah of of mitzvah, if it's on
Sukkot, so עד שבעה יומין לא הוי חזקה בתר שבעה יומין הוי
חזקה. ad shiva yomin lo hovei chazaka basar shiva yomin hovei chazaka.
So then actually only up to seven days it's not a chazaka
because, you know, obviously he'll let you do it for the period
of the chag, but if he doesn't say anything after the chag
is over, after seven days, then clearly that means that he is
giving you rights to leave it there, you know, because maybe leave
it there I know until next Sukkot or whatever it is, because
since now is the normal time to take it down and you
haven't and he hasn't said anything, that proves you have a right.
Tosfot says we don't really mean seven, we mean eight because Shmini
Atzeret, you're not taking it down on Shmini Atzeret. Okay.
Or nine actually for also for Simchat Torah. Okay. ואי חיבריה בטינא
לאלתר הוי חזקה, V'ei chivreh b'tina l'altar hovei chazaka, and if however,
presumably in either of these cases, you plastered it up, you know,
that and
the crossbeam and he didn't say anything, then that immediately establishes, again
presumably he saw, he had time to react or whatever, that immediately
establishes your right to continue doing it. So clearly by the way,
the ראשונים Rishonim point to this word לאלתר, la'altar, but the גמרא
Gemara already said thirty days, seven days, to show we're clearly not
talking about like the three-year חזקה chazakah and it's not talking about
purchasing, it's talking about establishing rights to use something.
Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said Abaye. שני בתים משני צידי רשות
הרבים. shnei batim mishnei tzidei reshus harabbim. You have two houses on
opposite sides of the public thoroughfare. זה עושה מעקה לחצי גגו וזה
עושה מעקה לחצי גגו וזה שלא כנגד זה ומעדיף. zeh oseh makeh
l'chatzi gago vezeh oseh makeh l'chatzi gago vezeh shelo keneged zeh umadif.
Okay, now you have the problem about היזק ראיה hezek re'iah and,
and there, you know, there, there're two חצרות chatzeros here, and, and
rather that you can't build a wall in the middle and make
each one pay half, so what do you do? So each one,
you know, builds half of the wall on their side. One builds
it from like, you know, starting at the north moving south, the
other builds it at the south moving north, and there's a little
overlap because if there's no overlap, you know, they're, they're apart from
each other, you can just see in at an angle, you know,
if you're standing at an angle you can see in between the
break, but if there's no overlap, then your view if you're standing
on the roof is blocked because of, because of your wall or
if you move to the right of your wall, it's blocked because
of his wall, each person cannot see into the other person's yard.
Okay.
Now תוספות Tosafos has an interesting point if you look at תוספות,
Tosafos, he says אומר ר"י דוקא בשני צידי רשות הרבים שאין אחד
מרגיש בחבירו כשעולה בגגו שיזהר ממנו דאמרינן סמוך בין בגג לגג לא.
Omer Ri davka bishnei tzidei reshus harabbim she'ein echad margish bechavero kesho'leh
begago sheyeizahar mimenu midamrina samucha bein begag legag lo.
That, you know, we normally understand of היזק ראיה hezek re'iah between,
in between two חצרות. chatzeros. And we'll see, you know, and again,
we also referenced this before, a גג gag and a חצר, chatzer,
a גג gag and a גג, gag, those may or may not
be, you know, those are not necessarily the same in terms of
היזק ראיה. hezek re'iah. So the גמרא's Gemara going to say that
a normal case of two roofs right adjacent to one another is
not a problem of היזק ראיה hezek re'iah because, you know, people
don't use it as an ongoing basis and you know when the
other person is there so you can avoid it and so on.
However here, because you're on opposite sides, you don't know if the
other person is there so there is a היזק ראיה hezek re'iah
problem and here's how you solve it that each one provides half
or fifty-one percent.
So now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay. מאי איריא ברשות הרבים אפילו ברשות היחיד נמי? mai irya birshus
harabbim afilu birshus hayachid nami? Why are you mentioning a רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim even if they're divided by a private street? Why specifically
by a public street? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, רשות הרבים
איצטריכא ליה. reshus harabbim itztarchlei. No, רשות הרבים reshus harabbim was a
חידוש. chiddush. מהו דתימא נימא ליה סוף סוף הא בעית איצטנועי מבני
רשות הרבים, mahu d'teima neima lei sof sof ha ba'is tznuyei mibnei
reshus harabbim, why doesn't Reuven say to Shimon, you build your whole
wall, I don't care about a wall, and you're telling me, you
know, go ahead, look at what I do, I don't care, I'm
not, היזק ראיה hezek re'iah doesn't bother me. But Shimon says, no,
I'm bothered by it and we have to build a wall and
you have to do half. So why can't Reuven say back to
Shimon, look, even if it wasn't for me, you would be building
a wall so the people down in the public domain aren't looking
up at you? So that's your business, you would build it anyway
because of them, I have nothing to do with it, don't make
me pay half. That seems to be a reasonable claim. But the
גמרא Gemara says, no, קא
משמע לן דאמר ליה, k'mashma lan de'amar lei, Shimon can say back
to Reuven, רבים ביממא חזו לי בליליא לא חזו לי. rabbim beyomama
chazi li baleila lo chazi li. No, in the, if it would
just for the people in the street, they could see me in
the daytime, they wouldn't see me at night time, and I wouldn't
bother building a wall if it was just for them. Okay, but
את בין ביממא בין בליליא חזית לי. at bein beyomama bein baleila
chazis li.
You, you're at the same height, you know, and therefore you'll be
able to see what I'm doing even at night, and I am
building this wall because of you, not because of them. אי נמי
inami or you could say, רבים כי קאימנא חזו לי כי יתיבנא
לא חזו לי. rabbim ki kyamina chazi li ki yasivna lo chazu
li. You know, down, they're down below, they have to look up,
so they'll only see me when I'm standing, they won't see me
when I'm sitting. So therefore again I wouldn't have bothered building if
it was just for them. רבים כי קאימנא... את חזית לי בין
כי קאימנא בין כי יתיבנא. at chazis li bein kyamina bein kyasivna.
You'll see me sitting or standing so I really am building this
wall because of your looking into my property.
Also, רבים כי מעייני חזו לי כי לא מעייני לא חזו לי.
rabbim ki me'aynu chazu li ki lo me'aynu lo chazu li. Also
down there, they have to be really looking up intently to see
me. So I'm not so concerned about it, you know, there'll be
a little obvious. את ממילא נמי חזית לי. at mimmela nami chazis
li. You'll just in passing see what I'm doing, you present a
much bigger היזק ראיה hezek re'iah and therefore even if you don't
care, you're obligated to do half.
Okay, that all those sound like good, very good arguments. אמר מר:
Amar Mar: זה עושה מעקה לחצי גגו וזה עושה מעקה לחצי גגו
וזה שלא כנגד זה ומעדיף. zeh oseh makeh l'chatzi gago vezeh oseh
makeh l'chatzi gago vezeh shelo keneged zeh umadif. So each one does
half and they overlap a little bit. So the גמרא Gemara says,
פשיטא, peshita, that's obvious, each one has to do their half and
presumably it's also pass... obvious that they have to, that they need
to overlap. לא צריכא דקדים חד מינייהו ועביד. lo tzericha dekadim chad
mineihu ve'avid. No, what we're, we'll talk about a scenario that one
of them already went and did his half. All right. מהו דתימא
mahu d'teima מהו דתימא נימא ליה אידך שקול זוזנך ועבדי את כולה,
mahu detema neima lei idach shkol zuznach ve'avdei at kuleih,
I would think maybe that the other guy can say to him,
you know, you listen, take the, what do you call it, the
expenses, you already did half, so and so I'll just pay you
the expenses and you go ahead and you, you know, you finish
the whole thing up.
קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, you know, maybe he doesn't want,
he doesn't want to have a wall on his property, it'll crowd
out, you know, it'll compromise some of his usable space. You've already
started building it, so I'll just pay you, you finish it. קא
משמע לן, ka mashma lan, so this teaches us דאמר ליה את
מאי טעמא לא עבדת משום דמירתע אשיטך אנא נמי מירתענא אשיטאי. d'amar
lei at mai ta'ama lo avadat mishum demitra'e ashitech ana nami mitre'ina
ashiti. No,
so he can say back to him. He can say, look, why
do you not want to do it? You don't want to build
a wall because you don't want your wall to be, I gave
a reason that you don't want to sort of compromise your usable
space, the גמרא Gemara says you don't want a wall to weigh
down on the building below, and on the wall below, you'd rather
not have anything there. So the same is true for me. So
even though I already built half, that doesn't mean that we take
that as a given and now we're just debating the second half
and you can make that claim. No, it's always my responsibility to
build half on my side and your responsibility to build half on
your side. Okay, we will stop here.